this video is sponsored by squarespace
the best place to build your portfolio
all right here's the final cut pro
grading tutorial you will have wished
you watched
earlier we're going to cover everything
from the basics of transforming your log
footage to making it look really
cinematic
and there's a lot of ways to color grade
in final cut there's no one correct way
to do it but there's
a lot of wrong ways to do it so i'm
going to lay things out in the simplest
way i can we're going to move
kind of quickly but by the end you'll
know the right way to do this without
screwing up your footage or picking up
too many bad habits on the way so i'm
going to use this commercial that we
shot a while ago for a brand called
northwater and you know what you're
after is probably something like this
let's look at the before and after of a
final here
here's one way that this could have that
cinematic look but
i don't want you to get too focused on
this end result because this part's the
easy part it's
everything before that that really
matters so let's get this back to a
neutral place i'm going to turn off all
those effects actually i'm going to
delete those effects
and just restore everything to the
original log that it was shot in so this
is what the footage looked like this
is canon log two c log two
first step before anything edit your
footage
i know it can be tempting to grade as
you go but if you're not finished
editing and you start grading you can
waste a lot of time
digging into files that you don't end up
using and it slows down your render time
so
finish your edit and then do a few
preference changes so i like to go into
final cut preferences
and under general you can choose the
default color correction method
i would absolutely not use color board i
always have it on color wheels which is
the most useful the most standard way of
adjusting colors
and so all that does is if i select a
clip and i go to the color adjustment
area
you can see this is what shows up by
default and that's what i like let's
also turn
on our scopes which you can find in the
view menu but i strongly recommend
remembering the shortcut command 7.
because i
turn them on and off a lot while i'm
editing so try to remember command 7.
the way i use mine is i go to view and i
show two of them at a time one is a
vector scope and the other is an
rgb overlay if you're not already sure
how to read these the vectorscope is
basically a saturation chart so if i
crank the saturation make this look
really bad you can see how saturated
each color is
in the image this will become very
important later on i'll show you how it
works
and then i use rgb overlay as my
waveform
a lot of people choose luma that's
really common advice
but i find you actually lose information
here and i'll show you why rgb overlay
is
much more useful later all this will
make sense in a bit another little thing
setting up final cut for grading is
you're going to want to grab an
adjustment layer i've got some links to
free ones you can download in the
description
to oversimplify what this does
everything below it ends up inheriting
the look that you give it so you've seen
those files now if i turn on the effects
they all change in the exact same way so
that they can all
match you can imagine why this is handy
but for now we're going to delete it
come back to it later just get it
installed so you're ready and the last
thing on your checklist make sure you
have the transform luts for the log
file that you're working with if you
shot in log i'll explain how to use that
right now let's get into this log
profiles these super flat to saturated
things are very common in modern
cameras i mean i'm shooting in it right
now for example even the new iphone 12
can shoot in 10 bit log which is
very impressive but it's the best way to
get the most
image quality out of your your colors
and your dynamic range
if you're not shooting a log things are
simpler you can skip this chapter you
could of course do it yourself so let's
look at the most basic things if i click
on this clip
i could go over here to my color wheels
bring the shadows down
and looking over at my waveform on the
left here i can see once they start
getting near zero that means they're
almost black then i could bring my
highlights
up until they start getting kind of
close to 100 i never want them to
actually clip but they're you know sort
of touching that 100 line
and then bring back the saturation which
i prefer to do mostly in the mid tones
and highlights a little less in the
shadows
you can see something like that that's
basically restoring the color and
contrast to this image
but i don't recommend doing it manually
like that you should go find a good
transform so for example part of the
reason i really like the c200 is it
transforms really
cleanly like it looks great as soon as i
add
one simple lut which in my case this is
a
lot that i adapted from the alexa
transform so
we can put on the log 2 and you can see
it really brings it back to looking
beautiful so when you see people's
before and after and they show the log
image and then they show this like
that's not interesting that's really
really easy everything else is the hard
part okay but what did i just do i
skipped around a lot here so
over here on the right uh you know
there's the overall inspector this is
where our filters will end up showing up
there is the
color inspector this is where our wheels
are and some of the other tools that if
you click here you can get a preview
we'll play with them later
and on the info tab here there is
camera lut now this is one place that
you can place your transform it is the
simplest workflow method
and if i go back and i select again the
the lut here
it's very easy to stay organized and you
could i could select everything and i
could apply that same
lutch to all the files that i'm working
with in this case though i'm also
working with some stock footage
so you got to be careful not to apply it
to the wrong thing and the best time to
use that method is with controlled
lighting so
here's another different example this is
a recent youtube video
and everything's basically the same
right just like this video i'm recording
now i'm sitting in the exact same place
not much is changing shot to shot and
here's a very good trick if you have a
long take like
me talking i i'm going to open it up and
you can see that i've actually put it in
a compound clip
the way to do a compound clip is just
select any video and press
option g and then inside that clip
any changes you make will show up
everywhere so if i go in here i can turn
my effects on now you can see my color
grade
if i click back it changes all of the
talking shots so i don't have to go back
and grade each clip individually it can
be really hard to keep that in sync
if you have a long clip put it inside a
compound clip
but now if we look at our commercial
again a lot of this is shot outdoors
there's a lot more dynamic range and
shifting light
values and stuff so we want to be more
careful with it
so we're going to do this the slightly
more complicated way i'm going to select
the clip
go to the effects menu over here and
inside of color i'm going to select
custom lut and i'm just going to drag
that over and drop it onto my clip now
you can see up here in effects we now
have custom lut
and i'm going to use my alexa adapted
lut that i like for c log2 and there we
go
same effect as before the big difference
here is now i can make adjustments
before the transform does that make any
sense at all i'm going to try to show
you right here so
if i drag this lut onto a clip and i add
this is the incorrect transform so this
is a c log 2 transform to a c log 1 clip
let's say i want to recover those clouds
so i drag my highlights down see how
they're just becoming gray but there's
no detail there
well if we look over at our effects
stack here like these are applied in the
order you see them so the top is first
and goes towards the bottom
if i move that adjustment above my
transform
all of a sudden i've recovered all of
those highlights like that's a huge
difference
this is what happens if you try to make
your adjustments after your transform
light
this is what happens if you apply them
before your transform light and this
info panel is the first step in this
stack
of of lut so if i apply it here there is
no way for me to then
later recover all that information and
maybe you're already stuck at this point
you're like wait i don't have a nice
transform lut that makes my footage look
beautiful well there's a lot of options
out there i'll put some links in the
description below so you can find some
of them
my favorite unfortunately isn't on final
cut pro yet it is called cinematch it's
coming soon it's available on
premiere and resolve right now but there
are luts for
all the different camera manufacturers i
don't really like the canon ones or the
sony ones
because let's say you're shooting on an
8-bit camera like an eos r
or an a7s2 or something like that those
transform luts from canon and sony
assume
that you have the more professional
cameras they didn't really design them
for the consumer cameras and the
transforms look weird and why am i
explaining this examples help
more so let's look at the built-in
transform the final cut comes with so
this is
for canon log2 and we compare it to the
one that i'm using
there's a whole world of difference so
compare some of the different transforms
and choose one that you like
again links in the description below
including you can purchase the ones that
i use if you want so now we want to make
all the footage that was shot on the
c200 look the same so i'm going to
select that clip hit command
c for copy and go to other clips and
press command
shift v like command shift paste
and now you can choose exactly which
video attributes you are going to apply
i don't need to apply the scaling
transform just the lut so i'm going to
turn that
off paste and now this clip also looks
good so let's do that to everything
and now as we flick through we can see
that everything
looks contrasty it looks like proper
footage transform complete but there's
still a lot to learn about them don't
think you've mastered it because you've
just found one lut that kind of works
in fact if you have a lut pack and all
of them just have like standard log
transform don't use that it doesn't
really work step two
correction so this is at least as
important as transforms
if you don't have your colors looking
accurate all those
fun filters and luts you're gonna add
later are gonna look like crap so
you gotta lay a foundation first and
that's what we're doing so these shots
look
pretty good overall i mean you know it'd
be nice to do this on one of the most
majestic
shots because it just looks good but um
i think i could demonstrate it more
clearly in a little
simple b-roll shot like this so first of
all
we want to be adjusting for both the
white balance and skin tones
in this case we're looking at the white
balance and what i'm looking at here is
over here on the left hand side
are our rgb overlay waveforms i can make
them a little bigger so i can
really clearly see them and without
looking at the actual image over here i
can tell that this is a little bit too
blue
because our blues are higher up here in
the highlights and there's also
something going on down here in the
shadows
so these shadows correspond to this dark
part of the backpack
and this streak going across the top
this is all that gray back there so this
should be
pretty neutral and fortunately it's
really easy to do that so we're going to
start by
creating a correction layer and first we
look at the highlights honestly you can
do it with this by
feel and just start like moving these in
a circle and you can see what happens
over there see those waveforms moving
around
i'm basically just going to keep moving
them until they start to
line up and converge
and once they're all in a line and white
that means
the white balance is now neutral can you
see that as i click it on and off this
like blue
cast just disappears that you didn't
even really see it before but now you
definitely see it when it goes away and
also let's keep our order of operations
correct here i'm going to move those
color wheels before our transform light
and also the shadows this dark area over
here
you can see that there's some color
visible in them where this should just
be straight up
black so as we move it around those will
gradually start to line up but keep an
eye on your highlights too like
everything is moving even though i'm
only grabbing the shadows
and sometimes if you move it until they
are perfectly aligned
like that now we have made our
highlights too warm
so we can bounce back and start to play
with our highlights again but there's
also such thing as
playing with it too much so kind of find
this balance where both of them
are mostly white and now if we turn this
on and off
you can see we got rid of a lot of color
cast there and then the other most
important thing is skin tone so
in this example we have lots of skin
tones to look at and we're going to use
our vector scope a little more for this
one so i'm going to make it a bit bigger
and i find it really helpful to just
crank the saturation when you're getting
started make it too saturated
and all of a sudden it gets really big
over here you can clearly see what's
going on
now make sure that in your vector scope
preferences you do have show skin tone
indicator on
and that is this subtle line that is
running
up and to the left and that is the
universal hue
level of skin tone regardless of the
complexion of the person whether they're
darker or lighter
the hue of their skin should be
somewhere pretty close to that line
in this example this orange roof up here
is actually kind of distracting us so
i'm going to zoom
in a whole bunch now everything that
we're seeing the vectorscope like all
the orange stuff
is pretty much his skin and over here i
have a little bit of gray now i'm just
going to kind of
tweak both of those until they're you
know pretty much
lining up right on it and then i can
restore that saturation back to normal
and zoom back out you know one more
thing you might have been considering is
you might have been looking at well what
about this temperature in tint slider
like
if we're going to be fixing the white
balance right like why don't i drag this
to be more yellow or more blue
let me try to demonstrate why i don't
like these if i start to move the
temperature slider to get her
skin over here to align with our skin
tone line
you can see that here in the highlights
it's starting to get like
weirdly yellow like if i drag this far
look at how yellow the highlights are
and the shadows
everything got super yellow it's really
not discerning about which parts the
image you're trying to affect
whereas if you were setting white
balance within your camera it would look
a lot more like this which here i'm just
grabbing the mid-tones and can you see
that i've got the skin right on the line
like it looks a lot better
but our highlights haven't moved so much
like our highlights are still neutral
which is exactly what we want we don't
want to add
weird coloration to different parts of
the image just to fix our skin or white
balance
so don't use the sliders use the color
wheels we're gonna look at the contrast
so there's a few things you could do
from color wheels like
you can bring your shadows a little
closer to the bottom if i look over to
the left you can see they're
almost touching zero i don't want them
to clip and go below zero
and then highlights can go up towards a
hundred
if there's anything that would be
clipped in your image then you could be
like
right at i'd put it at 95. but in this
photo nothing actually should be pure
white like those clouds aren't supposed
to be blown out so i'm going to keep
them down below
my white point of 95 which by the way
you can move this line i just
i set it here because for this project
95 is my white point that's actually up
to you
but now our image kind of makes sense
this doesn't let us affect what is
called
mid-tone contrast for that i'm going to
go here and use
color curves and a curve lets us be a
little more precise about where we are
moving the highlights and shadows up and
down towards the right are the
highlights and towards the left are the
shadows
and anywhere you click you add a point
so i'm going to add a point towards the
right for highlights
point towards the left for shadows and
i'll bring the shadows
a little bit down and the highlights a
little bit
up the classic s curve
and i think actually i'm losing too many
details in those shadows and this is
this is why i don't do with color wheels
i'm going to take that off i'm just
going to do this
inside of my color curves and this is
just a totally different
type of contrast like see how i can move
these points closer together
that contrast looks different from this
contrast
and this is up to you this is a creative
decision exactly where you want it to
land
you know i like to have what i call you
know a little bit of mid-tone contrast
by having these a little bit closer
together and
that that'll be different from your
other contrast so you add this
to taste it's up to you and before we
move on i want to emphasize why i don't
use the
luma waveform i'm going to make it
bigger so we can see what's going on
here if
i switch back to luma you can see that
it's only
barely bumping up against a hundred you
know looking at this waveform
everything seems fine nothing's really
clipping here from what i can tell
but if i switch back to rgb overlay you
can see there's actually a lot of the
blue channel
that has clipped that is past 100. that
is bad that is horrible like we have a
beautiful expensive camera here
and we're just making it look cheap like
these clips this looks
horrible this is what an old-fashioned
camcorder looks like
the reason you paid for your nice new
camera is so you could get
rich tones which you know basically they
have to be below 100
to do that so you can only see that
really clearly for me in the rgb overlay
so that i can see blue is now no longer
clipping and while we're on this clip a
final thing that i like to do
is i usually bring my mid-tones down a
little bit for
things i want to feel a little more
cinematic a little cinema
ish is um the the mid-tones coming down
gives it that sort of like richness of
tone let's do it to a few different
clips the best way i'd describe it is it
makes the colors
feel thicker like they're just kind of
more substantial whereas
if you're bringing it down say in the
highlights like it just looks darker and
and flatter
those mid tones coming down that's where
you get the the sort of the juice
the richness of of cinema so yeah i i
really like to
keep those a little bit low so something
in the image is kind of up near 95
but a lot of those mid-tones are coming
down towards the the lower half of
of the waveform and by the way 10-second
rant it is offensive to me
that photo editing apps do not have
these waveform functionalities these
scopes inside of them things like vector
scopes
are essential to me why can't i check my
skin tones in photoshop the same way i
can in final cut pro
it's totally insane and maddening that
yeah photography doesn't have these
basic monitoring tools
i don't understand it anyway back to
back to final cut now there's another
trick i have up my sleeve i do this
very often where i'll add what is called
a hue saturation curve
and go into it and look for saturation
versus saturation now everything on the
right is the most saturated parts of the
image the left
is desaturated what i do is add a few
points
on the right side and bring it down so
what this means
is that the most saturated parts of the
image
are a little less saturated like i don't
go crazy with it
it's a very gentle slope but if you i
turn it on and off you can see that it's
those blues that are just
way more saturated than her skin for
example
it helps bring everything a little bit
more into the same
saturation value sometimes i find
oranges sort of clip
and this just kind of brings it back
whatever the color is
it'll recover some of those clipped
saturation points
now let's get into the fun part adding
film emulation adding some looks
but first a quick thank you to our
sponsor squarespace
now whatever kind of filmmaker you are
i'm just going to guess that you might
sometimes want to show your work off to
the rest of the world
am i right well squarespace is the best
possible way to do that they help you
create portfolios either for filmmaking
or photography by embedding your work in
the highest quality
and surrounding it with a website that
is all your design
you can post things on social media that
can get lots of views but you don't
actually control that
and it can get shut down at a moment's
notice so don't rely on another platform
to keep your precious work online
invisible
take control with squarespace you're
going to be able to design every aspect
of it in just a few minutes it's really
simple
they have drag and drop templates that
are completely responsive created by
their professional designers
and then the back end is taken care of
for you so you can see all the analytics
that you're going to need
the seo is done for you you really don't
have to learn anything to run
a professional website even if you
already know how to do one it's so much
easier to let squarespace take care of
it for you
so i'd highly recommend go to
squarespace.com and just spend a few
minutes
designing your new website and then when
you are ready to launch
you can head to squarespace.com
tylerstallman to get 10
off your first website or domain i've
used squarespace for more projects than
i can count and they all look completely
different because it's so easy to work
with so thanks again squarespace
link in the description moving on to
luts this is the fun part this is when
you can go crazy first of all let's put
an adjustment layer over top
of everything now all you have to do is
drag it on top
it's a title by the way it's inside of
this title menu and i'm just going to
extend it
to cover our whole video here because
what we're trying to do is
add a unifying color grade to everything
that kind of brings it all together i
use the same lut
for pretty much everything again we're
going to go into our effects over here
i'm going to drag over
custom lut and select the one that i
always do and even though i've used this
a million times it's never
perfect at the beginning uh you know
it's a pretty soft one like you might
want to push this further but
i'm going to play with it for now first
of all i don't even use it at 100 all
the time for this video
i will but it also does some things i
don't love so if we turn it on and off
let's watch our rgb overlay over there
you can see it's squishing the
highlights
a little more than i really want it to
so next in the chain
i'm going to add another color wheel and
i'm going to bring those highlights up
just a little bit more i don't want them
pushed quite that far down
let's take another look it's pretty good
and keep in mind anything you do on this
top layer is now going to be applied
to everything so you're going to have to
probably go through all your clips
again and kind of you know rethink them
a little like this
now feels a lot brighter than i want i'm
going to bring those mids down
this feels warmer than i want also feels
more saturated than
i want but there's really just no way to
do all of this in one pass you have to
go through it
multiple times comparing clip by clip
and it's also really useful to
use the compare to so if we go to window
show in workspace comparison viewer and
i could click save frame so now i'm
seeing
the frame that i was just on and i can
compare it to anything else so i'll go
to this other clip
with our same actress here and uh you
know look at things like oh is her hair
a similar shade of red is the saturation
similar it's their skin
on a similar level and just kind of sync
those up so whichever one i've selected
now that's the only one that i'm
affecting here here's something i don't
like that my lut is doing so i'm going
to manually fix it by going
to hue saturation curves i'm going to
use this eyedropper and select the grass
which is our kind of green area it
actually happens to be a little more
yellow
and i'm going to pull it towards being a
little more so
a little more green because to me this
is a little more
dead grass this is a little bit more a
live grass as you make changes like this
make sure that you flick through the
rest of the video
and be sure that it wasn't you know
damaging anything else like here we have
a lot of green in this one as well so
we'll just turn that on and off and yeah
it's also
better in this one i like this slightly
more cyan green here and here's another
one where i'd bring the midtones down a
little bit
by the way i said there's a million
different lights out there it's really
true like let's take a look at some
others
just to remind you there's not just one
way that things can look but i wouldn't
do a lot to do something like this
press command 7 to bring our scopes back
up you can see it's added a ton of green
to the highlights
this is a look you'll see in movies this
is like a legitimate thing to do
but i try to make sure you have control
over that don't let the lut
push your image that far because it's
really hard to bring it back
later so again if you go back to mine i
prefer things that really keep the
highlights and shadows clean and are
mostly playing with everything in the
mid tones
and now the final step we're going to
export it and look at it on a lot of
different devices look at it on your
phone put it on a white background watch
it on your tv
just see it all over the place and get a
sense of what it really looks like
because
everybody has a different device and you
want to have a sense of how it's going
to appear
wherever it's going to be seen and
there's a lot more to color grading in
final cut pro than i was able to go over
here but
i will help you out with it if you want
if you follow me on twitter i'm at
stalman and
same thing on instagram and if we had
more time there is so much more to color
grading in final cut pro than i have
time for today but if you have any
questions you can hit me up on twitter
i'm at stallman
or listen to the podcast installment
podcast it's got lots of great info from
creators you probably like and follow
but thanks for watching this video guys
and i'll see you in the next one
you